What's up, Michael? How are you doing?
Hello, hello. I'm doing awesome. So glad to be having an evening show with you instead of a morning show.
Well, it's even early evening for me because I'm two hours time difference than where I normally sit. I'm coming to you from Utah.
Oh, amazing. Amazing.
If only I had my motorcycle here. That would be the best part if I was in Utah.
Yeah, the nature is there. They're so good.
So yeah, yep. But I don't. I'm here for a conference. So I'm gonna work. It'll be okay.
Yep. All right. Sounds good. Ready to hit this? Let's do it. Okay, let's do it.
Hello, and welcome to Python Bytes, where we deliver Python news and headlines directly to your earbuds. This is episode 487 recorded Tuesday, July 8, 2026. I'm Calvin Hendricks
Parker. I'm Michael Kennedy. Nice to have you, Michael. Thanks for joining me today.
We are sponsored by us. So check out the Talk Python courses. Your co-host, Michael here, has put a tremendous amount of effort into making sure every last human being on the planet can learn
Python like nobody's business. So excited to have that. And then check out Six Feet Up. I am the co-founder and CTO of Six Feet Up. We love solving hard problems. We're hiring. So if you're looking
for a position, go check out our careers page. I'll put that little plug in there. And make sure you connect with the hosts online. We are on all the socials. You can find Michael, myself, and the
show over on Mastodon, Bluesky, X, LinkedIn. I'm mostly active on LinkedIn. Michael, where are you
mostly active at? Where people talk to me. Otherwise, I'm not that active. So we'll go at
Michael and tell him something interesting. Yeah, there you go. Send in a show idea.
Send in a show idea. That's a great idea.
So if you want to join us live on YouTube, we do record this live.
So you can watch it all of its liveness at pythonbytes.fm/live.
Be part of the audience, usually Tuesday mornings, but today is Tuesday afternoons.
The older video versions are also available on that YouTube channel too.
And finally, if you want a handcrafted artisanal digest of every week's show, and get all the notes, make sure you add your name and your email to our friends of the show list.
And we never share those emails, but you will get a great list of links and things to go dive into right into your inbox.
All right, Michael, let's kick it off.
I love shell scripts and the little utilities, and it seems like you got a good one for us.
I know you're a fan of the shell world.
And, you know, let me introduce this topic by way of a sad face.
So I use Sentry for all the server stuff, and I get a notification from Sentry saying operational failure for, I don't know, what are the smaller apps that I run, like an API or something?
And it says that slash temp is full, and it can't write to it.
I'm like, well, that doesn't make any sense, because that's just like the Docker image, So I can just write to like this 150 gig hard drive that I have dedicated to just Docker volumes and Docker build data, like image data and stuff.
Something else has gone awry.
Oh, no, no.
It was right.
So I go in there and I'm like, pull up Btop, which I love Btop.
And it says, oh my God, it's so good.
And it's 100% full, all red, no green.
I'm like, oh God, it's right.
What is going on here?
I've been playing with switching to multi-step, multi-image, multi-stage builds with Docker.
And apparently those builds take up a much more image space if you don't clean up the old ones for some reason.
I don't know why. I don't really care.
But I do care that it was out of space.
And I'm like, what is going on? What can I get rid of?
So I typically run like a Docker system prune type thing, and it's okay.
But I'm like, well, let me just give this a look.
And if you want to ask for file size on a Linux terminal, it's not the easiest.
I mean you can do it in DU you can't say DU but you know you get it in bytes you're like what are these huge numbers they're like they don't make any sense to me now actually when it recursive for the folders and wouldn't it be great if it said this GB and I know there are flags you
can pass it to you if you remember the incantation but wouldn't it be nice if there was a better way so I want to introduce you to dust so it's a more intuitive version of DU built and rust the rust
part doesn't really matter what does matter is both that it gives you sizes in human terms
and it gives you a graph oh graph that's even better yeah and i like the tree structure too that you get to see that the tree i use like br root or b root for seeing like tree structures
but now this may do all of it yeah exactly so you can ask it's kind of like tree and it's kind of like DU but it gives you the disk size information in the tree view and on the right
hand side there's actually a visual graph that like plots them and it sorts it by size so you can see the bigger ones are at the bottom I think you can invert that if I remember that's
how I had run it and so you can actually just say show me the big stuff first in a hierarchical way so like what folder is like the word where do I start to make this thing run again and not
happen not do this again where it runs out of space so I started playing around with this thing and I thought this is pretty dope man I really like it you can
just curl install it cargo install it brew install I brew what did I if I was doing on Mac I would brew install it yeah but I think I cargo installed on Linux I can't really remember but anyway it got installed on the Linux somehow
And there it is.
So yeah, it's really nice, I think.
I mean, not a whole lot more to say.
There's tons of options for how you run it.
Actually, it lists a whole bunch of alternatives.
This is kind of a nice shout out to like, hey, there's like six other tools that do this, but here's why I wrote this still, you know what I mean?
Yeah.
It simply does the right thing when it handles lots of small files and directory, keeps the output simple by only showing larger entities and so on and so Yeah. Anyway.
That's cool.
I think it shows that if there's an itch to scratch someplace, someone's going to scratch it.
If you've got a better idea for an implementation of a tool, you should go do it.
And this dust one looks really awesome.
And I'll be installing it momentarily.
Sweet.
Yeah, I really like it.
So I can recommend and it's, I mean, I was able to just do like a Docker cleanup real quick and fix stuff, but I still like, well, where is all the space?
Because that's bigger than before.
So let me just like, I have plans and this has helped me form a plan.
nice i love the plans speaking of plans uh the next item i'm going to present to you is actually more of a specification and it's a proposal for a specification as opposed to something you can use
today but i really want this to exist so i felt like i needed to highlight the fact that the fine folks at astral the ones who got absorbed into a nice frontier model company are still doing
interesting work and this one is building a way better archive format for python packaging called war. Now, Michael, I know you're going to say I've heard of the war format before. And it's true.
I don't know. I've only heard of the raw format.
Really?
I don't know if I've heard of war. I know what war is, but not as a compression form.
This has nothing to do with the war format from the Java world. The Java had a web archive that you could basically deploy serverless into like a Tomcat server. You throw a war file into a
directory and poof, you've deployed an application. This is also packaging for Python applications but it's going to be optimized.
Given that it's Astral doing the work, they're optimizing around speed.
Speed, ease of use, reliability, resilience to failure is the goals for this specific format.
So it's a new archive format.
Basically, their goal is to be faster than Zip or Tar from the standard Python library so that you can actually make speed still be the main feature when deploying software.
It has support for three kinds of entities like files, directories, and links, three kind of compression modes, store, deflate.
And if you've never used ZStandard or ZSTD, you know that it can compress tremendously faster and more than standard GZIP can.
So it's also atomic, which I think I'm hoping this comes to fruition because how many times have you ever unzipped a file for it to crash halfway through and you're left with a directory full of some of the stuff, not all the stuff.
You don't know how much of the stuff.
That's one of their goals, is actually to make the unpacking atomic.
If it fails, you end up with the directory of nothing.
If it works, you get everything.
My favorite part of that scenario is if you are replacing something when you're unzipping it.
Yeah.
Then it fails.
You're like, oh, oh no.
Right, right, right.
So yeah, it gets back into the kind of the unambiguity of this.
unlike tar there should only be one way to express a given concept in the war because you know with tar files you can have bzips and gzips and non-compressed so there's really
just one extension and one command and it should be intuitive to use so it's not optimized for
maximal compression but for speed and indexability and then also this like per member compression support. So the idea is you could actually have, if this is meant for more streaming operation,
so be very compatible with sending out zip distributions or war distributions to, say, your edge servers. You want that to be fast, efficient, only copy the bits it needs so it
can understand what parts it has and what parts it doesn't and copy them a lot faster. So I'm excited for this proposal to move forward. There's a link here to the GitHub spec. There's a couple
friendly faces who are the current authors of said spec over here. So I think that this is very, very promising. And like other things from Astral, I anticipate it'll be well executed.
Looks very cool. Yeah. I had Charlie Marsh on a few weeks ago to talk about Astral moving into OpenAI and what does it mean for uv and different things.
Well, now they're not focusing on TYX, they can focus on this.
Exactly. Yeah. So I think it's pretty interesting that, you know, lots of new stuff and not just releases, but new initiatives are coming out. That's cool.
Yeah, no, definitely. Yeah. So short, sweet doesn't exist yet, but keep your eye on this space. I assume it'll be open source and so people can contribute.
I would, I would definitely think so. Yeah. So let's, let's talk about a fun topic.
I'm excited about this one.
Agents.
And I don't even know, I don't even have the words to talk about this right, because it's so overloaded, this term agent and agentic.
So if I'm using co-work, it's agentic.
But also if I'm using something that just uses tools and takes multiple steps, it's agentic.
If I have like a gas town full of people running around, burning, but my credit's doing weird like stuff, that's like, you know what I mean?
Like it's just, there's so much non-clarity.
And with that, I introduce to you Hermes agent.
Another one.
Here's another one.
And this one follows in the open claw realm, but it's a little bit of a research project.
And I think it's interesting.
So, Hugo Bown Anderson actually introduced me to this.
Although I mean, it's lots of people know about it.
I've talked about it that I've heard nothing more than I kind of think back.
Right. So the idea is it's kind of like open claw and that it's something that continuously runs and it's by no research, open source MIT, etc.
And it's written in Python, which is very interesting. So if I go over here to the GitHub, this thing is madness.
I've been I made a fork of it because I'm I had to customize something and it is like every day or two days I'll be like, oh, I should sync up the fork because I think it's changing fast.
350 commits. I'm like, oh man, that was like yesterday I synced it. 211,000 GitHub stars.
People are using this thing, it seems like. So here's the idea. It's like OpenClaw in that,
let's say it's not like ChatGPT or even let's say, co-work. So Anthropics co-work is really cool
because what you can do is give it tasks and it can use tools like i've taught claude how to use my notion so i can say hey claude i want you to do this analysis and then save it in this notion page
or something and it'll just do it which is cool but what it doesn't really seem to do is it doesn't cross coordinate and know about the different actions like you have a project that it could
do one thing but another project doesn't know about that other project and so this hermes thing like learns a ton and it's like self-improving self-programming so it keeps a memory of you
which I know other ones do but you could ask it to hey generate some skills for me and just save them and make them available any other time that I might ask about skills oh and could you reprogram yourself a little bit because this isn't working right yeah sure no problem I'll change my
internals you just got to restart me real quick if you don't mind because I can't do that to myself so it's just really got a lot of neat connectors and this sort of self-improving thing
is super cool so Calvin let me give you an example of just one of the things and I'll give you two examples but I will demonstrate one oh live demo nothing like a live demo on a new show
so I have my notice my Apple watch notice it's the it's just the face it's not and I haven't done anything to it.
Watch this.
Tell Hermes.
What's the text?
Send Calvin Hendrix Parker an email using my Talk Python account.
And I want the title to be, hello from the live show, and the body to be, check this out, man.
Done.
There you go.
So I didn't even touch my watch.
I just told it to do that.
And it's using a bunch of different skills to figure out how to send emails to which account should it use.
It's composing the email.
And it's going to send it to you in a little bit.
And you could connect all sorts of LLM backends.
Like that's right now using ChatGPT 5.5.
But you could do local models.
You could use Claude.
You could do GLM, whatever.
Like whatever you want to connect to it.
And multiple ones.
You can switch them around.
So that's pretty cool.
And while I'm waiting on that, the other thing is like this will give you a sense of the self-programmability.
So I was sitting on the couch and my daughter, I just got her a little dirt bike thing.
And she's like, we somehow ran across this private motocross track that had like a kid track side of it that was really perfect for like some off-road riding.
She's like, can we really go to that?
The problem is it only opens twice a month for a few hours, like four hours at a time.
And the times vary.
And the only way you know is if you go on their Facebook page.
And I'm not really on Facebook.
I'm like, how am I going to even keep track of this?
So I sat on the couch with my iPad, pasted the URL for the page, and then I just spoke to it.
I said, hey, here's the problem.
I'd like you to create a skill so that you can go do this and then create an automated job.
And by the time, five minutes later, it had built a skill, written some browser use code, and had set up a cron job.
So like three days a week, it will automatically do that.
and it'll send me an email if and only if new times appear in Facebook.
Just talking to it.
I didn't touch it.
I didn't program it.
It used Codex internally to write that for itself.
Yeah.
So on Hermes, what's their security stance?
It seemed like the open clock crowd was a little YOLO.
Let's go for it.
It's a little bit stronger.
It's still a weird world.
So the way I do it is I just have it running in Docker on my Mac Mini.
that's my work Mac Mini, but it's just always on, and it's my database server anyway.
So it's just running in a Docker container.
Yeah.
And it uses, like, I don't know, 600 megs of RAM.
Not terribly, terribly much.
Did you get an email?
Let me see.
I'm going to check my email.
Other cool things that it does is it, like, integrates with Discord.
So one of the main ways I talk to it is just through Discord.
You can have a text conversation.
Every new chat session becomes its own thread that then you can carry on.
and I taught it how to, like if I tell it to join the voice channel, it'll join the voice channel of Discord and it'll just have a conversation like you and I, but it'll keep a transcript somewhere else if I need to go see it.
I'm still waiting for the email to work its way through the inner tubes.
Oh, man. Anyway.
I'll give you a real-time update later in the show, I'm sure.
Yeah, we'll see.
So is there also a store, like an open store or marketplace of add-ons or is this you build your own?
which I think is probably a better idea for most people.
It has add-ons and it has skills.
But the main thing that you want to have as the add-ons are the connectors.
Yeah.
How does it, so it'll do daily briefings and save them to Notion in a database and so on.
You know what I just checked?
The problem is it wanted to run some script and ask for, do you want to allow, yes or no?
I said always, but it's a pretty new setup.
So the first time, Anyway, eventually you'll get an email now, I'm pretty sure.
But I think it's cool.
I've been playing a lot with it.
And yeah, there goes my free time.
Why did I play with this?
No, it's super fun to dream about what you might do with it.
That is super cool.
Well, Michael, I have another agent for you that's in a very different vein.
Like you said, there's all kinds of different agents available out there.
This one is by our friend Simon Willison.
So if you know Simon from the Django project and the data set work he's been doing and all the kind of advocacy and work he's been doing around AI and LLMs.
If you aren't familiar, he wrote a command line utility, again, another great command line utility called LLM.
Hard to search for because of the name that he used for it.
But if you just search for Simon and LLM, you'll find his normal command line LLM, which lets you just ask an LLM a question from the command line, get a response back.
He's been growing that with tons of plugins and add-ons.
So for example, I've got an LLM add-on called CMD that I use regularly, where you do LLM CMD, and you type like what you want to do.
Find me all the Python files that are one level deep in my directory.
You hit return, and it'll come back to a prompt ready for you to hit return with the find command that does exactly what you want.
So basically, it's kind of a shell extension to autocomplete with an LLM.
Hard to remember commands like DU flag options, for example.
Well, he's taken this to the next level.
he has built a plugin for LLM that is still very alpha. This is very, very early days. This only came out a couple days ago called the LLM coding agent. And so now you can install the coding agent
and you can do LLM code and you can give it a flag like --YOLO and have it build with tools. So he basically using Fable, he had Fable write this plugin to basically turn LLM into a
Claude Code-like experience. And it works with local models. So I installed the LLM Ollama
plugin, or the LLM CPP plugin. And I used a Quinn 3.5 MLX accelerated model on my MacBook Pro here.
And I wrote some CLI calendar tools really quickly with the, just from the command line, very, very lightweight, very, very low barrier to entry. It'll be interesting to see where this
goes because I like the lightweight nature of the LLM tool itself. I don't do you use the LLM tool at
all? From Simon? Yeah. No, I should. I haven't yet, though. It looks really cool. When you're
just sitting at your terminal and you need a quick answer or something, like you can put it on like the GPT mini or haiku for really quick, like quick, super quick responses. Or you can pass it, just
keep everything local. Like this fully runs locally on my own machine when I'm playing with it. So if want to play with it you need to shift as an alpha currently so you can uvx if you want to test it out
with the pre-release allow flag and then install it into your llm and run the code keyword and it'll just give you a prompt just like a clot code and now it has access to tools to read write list files
investigate and so it'll build up a picture of the files that are in that current directory and act like a coding agent here's a demo where we did it with gpt55 to build a swift UI cli clock And the demo is at the bottom of that page.
There's a GitHub repo because it's all open source.
But you can see here the prompts he used to actually write this plugin.
Two prompts, write the spec, implement the spec.
So that's pretty cool.
I'm excited for more to come.
I always love Simon's tools.
If you're not following Simon's blog, you should definitely go out there and follow Simon online.
So that's what I got.
I think Simon's doing really good work.
He is.
I think his writing, he's got a mini book type thing that's online.
for like coding.
For engineers.
Coding type of stuff.
Yeah, and that's really good.
A lot of neat stuff.
Man, he is just on so many interesting places.
He was on Talk Python a while ago to talk about something with Django.
Maybe it was his birthday, the birthday, like a big milestone birthday or something like that.
I was like, yeah, it was just on CNBC.
I got a, I'm sorry, I was late.
I'm like, you know what?
You're living a different world than most of the developers.
Congratulations, man.
Yeah.
But I like his pragmatic style.
He writes about it very realistically about what they're capable of and what they're not capable of.
And so if it took him this long to get around to writing a plugin for an agent, a coding agent for LLM, it must be about time.
So I feel like that's the timeline I like to follow.
Yeah.
All right, Michael, you got an extra for me?
I got some extras, but I also have a real-time follow-up real quick here.
So you mentioned Fable.
Yes.
Fable is open to the public.
it was back but it was back until July 7th which is today the time of the recording and then it was supposed to go into API only and then I just heard that it's supposed to be back permanently for the
max max subscribers and for everyone it's now available for one more week so if you're like if you're like I was gonna build something with it but I didn't get it done and that went away
it's back for one more week so we'll build that thing all right so all right last week I talked about PLS and I wrote a blog post like what the PLS man come on because I was a little frustrated
not know like a super frustrated just like look so people we'd recommend it we both on our all of our tools episode we recommend like oh that's so cool and people like yeah but I'm like what do you
mean but like yeah but you can't really install the like you follow the instructions and it doesn't it to you right there's like a bunch of stuff so i wrote this blog post called what the pls which
said like look it's not really doing what you want so please don't please don't uv pip install it instead what you should do is this well well well if you look at the top there's an update from not
too long ago and it says druv banu shali saw this post and decided to take he's the maintainer decided to take some action so that you can no longer be like freaked out about like what the
heck is going on so now if you go over to the GitHub issue which notice it is closed and um let me hover and get a name christian letterman yeah yeah i know christian
very cool and said hey um posted hey by the way um also tag this so actually um Drew said also tagging Mike C. Kennedy because he might be interested after seeing
and said hey guys look I'm sorry but uh now look you you got sub commented I did I did so if you go
over you know I said hey thanks so much and actually changed it such that even um if you go over here, just the latest release.
So UVPIP install PLS.
Now we'll install this one, which is the Rust version.
So you're back to good.
There's some other funkiness around this.
Read me on PyPI, but it says that'll be fixed when 7.0 comes out.
And 7.0 is almost out, but not out.
So yeah.
But look at this.
Woohoo.
Updated.
I love how developers sweat the small stuff sometimes.
I know.
there's a lot there's like layers of sweating the small stuff and i would like to just point out that christian did the right thing and posted a thing said hey dear project and maintainer of this
project it's just really kind of janky do you think you could maybe uh fix this like so it's not so confusing yeah whereas i just wrote like a not a hate pose but like a sort of frustrated
like, ah, don't do this. This is kind of not great. But just to the world. The only reason I did that and didn't create one of these is I was sure that they were just uninterested in fixing this because surely it would have been fixed by now if they'd known and wanted to, you know what I mean?
But no, I was wrong. So I should have followed Christian's lead and just posted this first.
Well, thanks Christian for doing the right thing.
Exactly. Well done.
That's cool. Very cool. Well, speaking of developers doing the right thing, I've got a couple extras here. If you are a developer that gives presentations at conferences,
you should check out SlideEv. I was at a conference two weeks ago, the AWS Midwest Community Day, and I, for the last six years, have been using Reveal.js via Pandoc and some cookie cutter
markdown glue that I put together to basically build my presentations with. I love Deerly because I handcrafted it, but I wasn't actually that in love with it. I'm going to move to this.
I found out this via Corey Quinn, so of the AWS Screaming in the Cloud fame.
He uses this to give his talks, and I saw his talk on stage.
I was, like, asking him afterwards what he was using, and it's slide dev.
So it's all markdown.
I like the way the markdown comes out a lot cleaner with slide dev than what I was doing.
I could do similar things, but it got a little messy and just didn't have the spirit of true markdown.
But here you've got the ability to turn markdown like this into slides like this.
So I would check it out if you give presentations.
It's got a ton of features.
Ton, ton, ton.
I'll click over on the features page real quick.
I mean, just remote presentations.
You can package it up as a PDF immediately.
You can put it into a CI pipeline and have a rendered version of it.
It's kind of fully baked.
You can have fully inline code that run.
So if you want to give demos during your talk, you can do that inline in your slides without leaving the deck itself.
Yeah, that's pretty cool.
and I found out it was using, I believe it's using MDX, which are Markdown Live components inside of the tool itself. So pretty cool. I'm going to be checking it out. The next time you
see me give a talk on the stage, it will most likely be using SlideDiv for it. Excellent.
Yeah. I love it. The last one here, I got two more. This one, I have not tried this yet, but if you want to reduce your token usage on Claude for use with Fable, for example,
Someone wrote a tool called PX pipe for pixel pipe that takes your text and encodes it into an image because Anthropic treats images differently token wise than it does the text.
They say they claim up to a 70% token reduction because of the handling of images versus like the text itself.
Now, if y'all could see the screen.
Yeah, yeah.
It's not just text.
It's really small text.
Black text.
Yeah.
It looks like a gray wall, but that's actually like the text of the prompt.
Now, there are downsides.
Be careful.
The honest part.
It is lossy.
Yeah, so it's lossy.
I wouldn't use it for real work.
It's workload dependent.
Your mileage may vary.
So I just thought it was interesting I'd share it with the crowd because some people might be interested in just token maxing on the other direction.
How many tokens can I save?
Which I thought was interesting.
Yeah, it's the anti-token.
I am not a fan of token maxing.
No, I'm not either.
I want to conserve the tokens.
Not just conserve.
I think there is an art and a skill to say, what is the least this thing needs to know so we can focus the most on it?
Not like, what is the maximum I can jam into its memory and still get it to accomplish something?
You know what I mean?
Yeah, exactly.
So really quick, before we wrap up extras,
do you have an email?
Oh, let me see. Let me go double check. Do I have an email? I don't see an email, Michael. Let me click refresh.
You don't see an email?
No. You sure? Did it send a six-feet up, I assume?
It did. It says it did. It said Talbot.
Maybe it's like, that's just too body, and you landed in the bot zone.
I might have gotten boted. Anyway, we'll review that later.
Okay. One last one last one last extra before we leave. Yeah, you had mentioned PEP 772, which is the Python Packaging Council. On a previous episode, I wanted to bring to everyone's
attention that the inaugural election dates have been set. The nominations are open until July 28.
And the voting will happen from September 1. to the 15. So if you're interested in the packaging council jump on the boat and go participate awesome awesome all right how about
a joke now so this one i hand selected for you calvin because i thought you might appreciate this and i i've entitled it minimum requirements for Linux okay i'm already i'm already in i'm
already in i know you're in and i this is putting Linux in a good light so it's mostly a picture but i'll just describe it too because it's fun like you know there's this big brouhaha about
windows 11 and tpm chips 2.0 so even if you have a tpm chip you're not enough for windows 11 like so you got to go buy yet another one i think Linux has a different uh deal here so the idea is
there's this i can't play it there's this old dirty nasty 486 looking thing that's found in like a ditch in the water probably like a hewlett packard yeah like a hewlett packard i mean it's got
like dvd drives and stuff yeah yeah yes or a compact maybe yes just in the water and in the
mud and they pull it out and go minimum requirements for Linux it will run it's a video sadly i can't play because i'm not logged in but apparently whatever you can play it when you log it i'll
I'll go long and play it, Michael.
Very good stuff.
Thank you very much, Michael, for this edition of Python Bytes.
We will see you all next week.
Thank you very much.
Yeah. Thanks. Bye.